and its botanical name, Eichhornia crassipes. Interestingly, in Nigeria, the plant is also known by other names, names associated with historical events, as well as myths. In some places, the plant is called Babangida. When you hear Babangida, you remember the military and military coups. And you think: fear, restraint. In parts of Nigeria in the Niger Delta, the plant is also known as Abiola. When you hear Abiola, you remember annulled elections and you think: dashed hopes. In the southwestern part of Nigeria, the plant is known as Gbe'borun. Gbe'borun is a Yoruba phrase which translates to "gossip," or "talebearer." When you think of gossip, you think: rapid reproduction, destruction. And in the Igala-speaking part of Nigeria, the plant is known as A Kp'iye Kp'oma, And when you hear that, you think of death. It literally translates to "death to mother and child." I personally had my encounter with this plant in the year 2009. It was shortly after I had relocated from the US to Nigeria. I'd quit my job in corporate America and decided to take this big leap of faith, a leap of faith that came out of a deep sense of conviction that there was a lot of work to do in Nigeria in the area of sustainable development. And so here I was in the year 2009, actually, at the end of 2009,
y su nombre botánico es Eichhornia crassipes. En Nigeria, esta planta también es conocida por otros nombres. Nombres asociados tanto a eventos históricos como a mitos. En algunos lugares, es llamada babangida. Babangida hace referencia al ejército y al golpe de Estado militar. Transmite miedo, restricción. En el delta del río Níger, esta planta también es conocida como abiola. Cuando oyes abiola, recuerdas las elecciones anuladas y te transmite "sueños hechos añicos". En el suroeste de Nigeria, la planta es conocida como gbe'borun. Gbe'borun es una expresión yoruba traducida como "cotilleo" o "rumor". La palabra "cotilleo" sugiere: transmisión rápida, destrucción. En la zona de Nigeria en la que se habla igala, la planta es conocida como kp'iye kp'oma. Cuando oyes esta palabra, piensas en la muerte. Se traduce literalmente como "muerte de la madre y el hijo". Me topé con esta planta en 2009, poco después de trasladarme de EE.UU. a Nigeria. Había dejado mi trabajo de corporativa en EE.UU. y decidí dar un gran paso, un gran paso basado en la convicción de que había mucho que hacer en Nigeria en el ámbito del desarrollo sostenible. Así que allí estaba en 2009, a finales de 2009 para ser exactos,
in Lagos on the Third Mainland Bridge. And I looked to my left and saw this very arresting image. It was an image of fishing boats that had been hemmed in by dense mats of water hyacinth. And I was really pained by what I saw because I thought to myself, "These poor fisherfolk, how are they going to go about their daily activities with these restrictions." And then I thought, "There's got to be a better way." A win-win solution whereby the environment is taken care of by the weeds being cleared out of the way and then this being turned into an economic benefit for the communities whose lives are impacted the most by the infestation of the weed. That, I would say, was my spark moment. And so I did further research to find out more about the beneficial uses of this weed. Out of the several, one struck me the most. It was the use of the plant for handicrafts. And I thought, "What a great idea." Personally, I love handicrafts, especially handicrafts that are woven around a story. And so I thought, "This could be easily deployed within the communities without the requirement of technical skills." And I thought to myself, "Three simple steps to a mega solution." First step: Get out into the waterways and harvest the water hyacinth. That way, you create access. Secondly, you dry the water hyacinth stems. And thirdly, you weave the water hyacinth into products. The third step was a challenge. See, I'm a computer scientist by background and not someone in the creative arts. And so I began my quest to find out how I can learn how to weave.
en el Tercer Puente de Lagos. Miré a mi izquierda y me topé con esta imagen impresionante. Había barcos pesqueros atrapados en esta maraña de jacintos de agua. Me afectó mucho lo que vi. Pensé: "Estos pobres pescadores, ¿cómo van a llevar a cabo su trabajo en estas condiciones? Y entonces pensé: "Debe haber alguna forma". Una buena solución con la que se proteja al medio ambiente, quitando de en medio estas malas hierbas, y se consiga transformar esto en beneficio económico para las comunidades que se han visto más afectadas por la invasión de esta planta. En ese momento se me encendió la bombilla. Investigué en profundidad para conocer mejor los usos beneficiosos de esta planta. Entre ellos, el que más me impactó fue su uso para artesanía. Pensé: "¡Qué gran idea!" Me encanta la artesanía, sobre todo, la artesanía que tiene una historia detrás. Pensé: "Esto puede introducirse fácilmente en las comunidades sin la necesidad de contar con destrezas técnicas". Se me ocurrieron tres sencillos pasos para una gran solución. Primero: Meterse en los canales y sacar los jacintos de agua. De esta forma, se crea acceso. Segundo: Secar los tallos de los jacintos de agua. Y tercero: Convertir los jacintos de agua en productos. El tercer paso era todo un reto. Tengo experiencia como informática pero no en artes creativas. Así que empecé mi aventura averiguando cómo aprender a tejer.
And this quest took me to a community in Ibadan, where I lived, called Sabo. Sabo translates to "strangers' quarters." And the community is predominantly made up of people from the northern part of the country. So I literally took my dried weeds in hand, there were several more of them, and went knocking from door to door to find out who could teach me how to weave these water hyacinth stems into ropes. And I was directed to the shed of Malam Yahaya. The problem, though, is that Malam Yahaya doesn't speak English and neither did I speak Hausa. But some little kids came to the rescue and helped translate.
Esta búsqueda me llevó hasta una comunidad en Ibadan, en la que viví, llamada Sabo. Sabo se traduce como "el barrio de los extraños" y la comunidad está formada mayormente por gente del norte del país. Así que, con las plantas secas en mi poder, tenía bastantes, fui de puerta en puerta, buscando a alguien que pudiera enseñarme a transformar estos tallos de jacinto de agua en cuerdas. Me enviaron a casa de Malam Yahaya. Sin embargo, el problema es que Malam Yahaya no habla inglés y yo tampoco hablo hausa. Pero unos niños vinieron al rescate y nos ayudaron a traducir.
And that began my journey of learning how to weave and transform these dried water hyacinth stems into long ropes. With my long ropes in hand, I was now equipped to make products. And that was the beginning of partnerships. Working with rattan basket makers to come up with products. So with this in hand, I felt confident that I would be able to take this knowledge back into the riverine communities and help them to transform their adversity into prosperity. So taking these weeds and actually weaving them into products that can be sold. So we have pens, we have tableware, we have purses, we have tissue boxes. Thereby, helping the communities to see water hyacinth in a different light. Seeing water hyacinth as being valuable, being aesthetic, being durable, tough, resilient. Changing names, changing livelihoods. From Gbe'borun, gossip, to Olusotan, storyteller. And from A Kp'iye Kp'oma, which is "killer of mother and child," to Ya du j'ewn w'Iye kp'Oma, "provider of food for mother and child." And I'd like to end with a quote by Michael Margolis. He said, "If you want to learn about a culture, listen to the stories. And if you want to change a culture, change the stories." And so, from Makoko community, to Abobiri, to Ewoi, to Kolo, to Owahwa, Esaba, we have changed the story. Thank you for listening. (Applause)
Así fue como empecé a aprender a tejer y a transformar estos tallos secos de jacintos de agua en cuerdas largas. Con estas cuerdas largas listas ya estaba preparada para hacer productos y ese fue el principio de las colaboraciones. Trabajé con fabricantes de cestas de mimbre para idear productos. Contando con todo esto, estaba segura de que podría llevar este conocimiento hasta las comunidades ribereñas y ayudarles a transformar su adversidad en prosperidad. Cogimos estas plantas y las tejimos, transformándolas en productos que pudieran venderse. Teníamos lápices, posavasos, bolsos, cajas para papel. De este modo, ayudamos a las comunidades a ver los jacintos de agua desde otra perspectiva. Los jacintos de agua podían ser valiosos, estéticos, duraderos, resistentes y elásticos. Cambiamos los nombres y la forma de ganarse la vida. De gbe'borun, cotilleo, a olutosan, narrador. Y de kp'iye kp'oma que significa "muerte de la madre y el hijo", a Ya du j'ewn w'Iye kp'Oma, "proveedor de comida para madre e hijo". Me gustaría terminar con una cita de Michael Margolis. Dijo: "Si quieres aprender de una cultura, escucha sus historias. Si quieres cambiar una cultura, cambia sus historias": Desde comunidades como Makoko, Abobiri, Ewoi, Kolo, Owahwa o Esaba, hemos cambiado la historia. Gracias por su atención. (Aplausos)